{
  "version": 2.0,
  "questions": [
    {
      "question": "1. An instrument detects the presence of electric current in the circuit, is known as,",
      "answers": {
        "a": "Galvanometer",
        "b": "Voltmeter",
        "c": "Rheostat",
        "d": "Wattmeter"
      },
      "correctAnswer": "a",
      "difficulty": "beginner"
    },
    {
      "question": "2. In a D’Arsonval galvanometer what is the purpose of using iron core between two pole faces ?",
      "answers": {
        "a": "The effect of stray magnetic field is reduced",
        "b": "Moment of inertia of moving parts become smaller",
        "c": "Cost of production is reduced",
        "d": "Flux density in the air gap becomes high, causing large deflecting torque"
      },
      "correctAnswer": "d",
      "difficulty": "beginner"
    },
    {
      "question": "3. Which is the most common absolute instrument that gives the measured current in form of the tangent of deflected angle ?",
      "answers": {
        "a": "Tangent Galvanometer",
        "b": "Tangent Voltmeter",
        "c": "Tangent Rheostat",
        "d": "Tangent Wattmeter"
      },
      "correctAnswer": "a",
      "difficulty": "beginner"
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Galvanometer connected with high resistance in series is used as ___",
      "answers": {
        "a": "Ohmmeter",
        "b": "Ammeter",
        "c": "Wattmeter",
        "d": "Voltmeter"
      },
      "correctAnswer": "d",
      "difficulty": "beginner"
    },
    {
      "question": "5. Sometimes D’Arsonval galvanometer does not use ferromagnetic cores between the poles of permanent magnet, in this case,",
      "answers": {
        "a": "The flux density becomes smaller, resulting in low deflecting torque.",
        "b": "The dimension of moving coil can be made smaller, thereby reducing moment of inertia.",
        "c": "The magnetic field may not be radial, resulting in a non-uniform scale even if spring control is used.",
        "d": "All of the above"
      },
      "correctAnswer": "d",
      "difficulty": "beginner"
    },
	{
      "question": "6. How does a galvanometer become an ammeter ?",
      "answers": {
        "a": "By wiring a high resistance shunt to the galvanometer in parallel.",
        "b": "By connecting a low resistance shunt to the galvanometer in parallel.",
        "c": "A high resistance shunt is connected in series with the galvanometer.",
        "d": "A low resistance shunt is connected in series with the galvanometer."
      },
      "correctAnswer": "b",
      "difficulty": "beginner"
    },	
	
	
	{
      "question": "7. Which one of the following meters is an integrating type instrument?",
      "answers": {
        "a": "Voltmeter",
        "b": "Ammeter",
        "c": "Energy meter",
        "d": "Wattmeter"
      },
      "correctAnswer": "c",
      "difficulty": "beginner"
    },
	{
	 "question": "8. The advantage of using galvanometers is ___________?",
      "answers": {
        "a": "High accuracy",
        "b": "High reliability",
        "c": "High sensitivity",
        "d": "All of the above"
      },
      "correctAnswer": "d",
      "difficulty": "beginner"
    },
	
	{
      "question": "9. A moving coil instrument has the following data.<br/> Number of turns = 100, width of the coil = 20 mm, depth of the coil = 30 mm, flux density in the gap = 0.1 Wb/m<sup>2</sup>. Calculate the deflection when carrying a current of 10 mA and the control spring constant is 2 &times; 10<sup>–6</sup> Nm/degree.",
      "answers": {
        "a": "6 &deg;",
        "b": "10 &deg;",
        "c": "30 &deg;",
        "d": "45 &deg;"
        
      },
      "correctAnswer": "c",
      "difficulty": "beginner"
    }, 
	{
	 "question": "10. The advantage of PMMC type instruments is _______",
      "answers": {
        "a": "They can be modified with the help of shunts and resistance to cover a wide range of currents and voltages.",
        "b": "They display no hystersis.",
        "c": "Since operating fields of such instruments are very strong, they are not significantly affected by stray magnetic fields.",
        "d": "All of the above"
      },
      "correctAnswer": "d",
      "difficulty": "beginner"
    }
	
  ]
}
